Jeffrey Michael Jackovich

<u>jeffrey.jackovich@gmail.com</u> • <u>github.com/JeffreyJackovich</u> Brooklyn, NY • jeffreyjackovich.com • linkedin.com/in/jeffrey-jackovich

Summary

Published data engineer with 10+ years of professional experience using Python and SQL to engineer scalable data pipelines in the healthcare and finance industries. Passionate building natural language processing (NLP) pipelines locally and on AWS. Strong engineering experience analyzing and processing structured and unstructured healthcare data to develop data products.

Skills

Languages: Python, SQL, R, Java

Statistics/Machine Learning: Statistical Analysis, NLP, Classification, Clustering, Regression

Tools and Libraries: Pandas, Numpy, Sklearn, NLTK, Spacy, Jupyter, Matplotlib, Selenium, Pytest, Git, Apache Spark, Cloudera Impala

Databases: MSSQL, Postgres, MySQL

AWS: Redshift, Lambda, S3, Glue, Comprehend

Experience

Senior Ideation Analyst / Engineer (Full Time), HMS Holdings, New York, NY

08/2020 - Present

- Work on a five person agile team to engineer a contract modeling application from ideation to production.
- Engineering an end-to-end Python ETL to extract competitive market share opportunities from unstructured medical claims.
- Built a Python NLP ETL to generate billing concepts from unstructured medical claims data using Spacy and Regex.
- Classified unstructured medical notes with 94 percent accuracy using Random Forests.
- Reprice claims by engineering a Python-based algorithm to rank from 400M+ SQL Server records.

Software Engineering Senior Advisor / Big Data Engineer (Contract), Cigna, New York, NY

11/2019 - 03/2020

- Worked on a seven person agile team to build a data pipeline from HDFS on-premises to AWS for a contract modeling application.
- Engineered a prototype ETL pipeline with Glue, PySpark, and Lambda to transform text files (15M+ records) to Parquet.
- Performed data quality analysis within Cloudera Impala using Hive/SQL and migrate masked PHI (Protected Health Information) data from HDFS on-premises to S3
- Identified columns in HDFS tables that contained PHI with a 99% recall score by re-engineering an open source NLP library.

Python Technical Analyst (Contract), Remedy Partners, New York, NY

03/2019 - 09/2019

- Worked on an agile team with four data engineers to perform data quality analysis with SQL and Python.
- Performed data quality analysis with pandas and SQL to identify and categorize duplicate records in Redshift and MySQL.
- Increased duplicate record detection by 11%, compared to SQL efficacy, by engineering a NLP algorithm that identified 10,000+ partial duplicates in 20M+ total Redshift records.

Machine Learning Engineer / Co-Author, Packt Publishing, New York, NY

05/2018 - 02/2019

- Translated Packt's authoring request for the title 'Machine learning with AWS' to both a book about natural language processing (NLP) algorithms and a Python-based NLP data pipeline.
- Architected a NLP data pipeline in Python with S3, Lambda, and Comprehend to output sentiment, key phrases, and entities from text documents.
- Developed 40+ Python programming examples to augment NLP concepts including topic modeling, latent dirichlet allocation, theme extraction, sentiment analysis, and entity detection.

Data Engineer, Freelance, New York, NY

01/2017 - 05/2018

- Privately contracted by a VP of Physician Development to engineer a lead generation data pipeline to identify, filter, and extract information on dermatology practices for acquisition.
- Enabled a client to meet a 72-hour lead-generation deadline by web-scraping a JavaScript website with Selenium and Python.
- Engineered a Python algorithm to integrate disparate lead generation data from social media APIs (e.g. Yelp, Twitter, etc.).

- Programmed a ranking algorithm on 2M+ records with Python and pandas to prioritize lead generation that resulted in a 10.0%, of total outreach, prospect attendance rate at M&A events.
- Created a valuation model from multiple data sources (e.g. medical records, claims, and tax forms) with pandas to identify risk factors in M&A deals of independent practice-owning physicians.
- Used pandas to join and transform disparate lead generation data (e.g. CSV, JSON, HTML, and XML) from open source APIs (e.g. Yelp, LinkedIn, etc.) with a custom ETL into a PostgreSQL data warehouse for lead generation analysis.

Education

MS, Computer Information Systems, Boston University, Boston, MA **BS, Biology**, Bradley University, Peoria, IL

08/2016 - 01/2019 08/2001 - 05/2006

• Minors: Psychology and Philosophy

Certification

AWS Technical Professional

01/2017

Publication

Jackovich, J., & Richards, R. (2018). *Machine Learning with AWS*. Birmingham, UK: Packt Publishing. ISBN-13: 978-1789806199 [https://amzn.to/2UuSZru]

Hackathon

Data Engineer, Mount Sinai Health Hackathon, New York, NY

10/2019

- Built an app for diabetic patients to speak their blood glucose levels to Alexa and receive dietary and exercise suggestions.
- In thirty-six hours, worked on an 11 person team from ideation to a MVP and competed against 20 teams.
- Built a Naive Bayes classification model from anonymized patient's time series blood glucose data to predict hypoglycemic outcomes.
- Technologies: Python, Node.js, Alexa, MongoDB, Heroku

Presentation

Jackovich, J. (2015, March). *Analyze Public Medical Data*. Presentation at the New York Machine Learning Workshop, New York, NY. [https://www.meetup.com/New-York-ML-Workshop/events/221103883/]